Register of the Zarko Rista Popovic Papers, 1917-1980
Hoover Institution Archives
Zarko Rista Popovic Papers
1917-1980
Popovic, Zarko Rista, 1896-1989
75108
Number of Containers: 4 manuscript boxes 1.6 linear feet
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The papers include diaries, correspondence, reports, memoranda, and clippings, relating to Yugoslav-Soviet relations, the Yugoslav coup d'état of 1941 March 27, relations of the Yugoslav Government-in-Exile with the United States and Great Britain, Draža Mihailović and the Yugoslav resistance movement during World War II, dissension within the Yugoslav resistance movement (especially as expressed in the so-called Cairo affair of 1942), and postwar Yugoslav émigré politics. Includes diaries, in Russian, for 1917-1931 and 1941-1975. Also available on microfilm (6 reels).
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1975.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Also available on microfilm (6 reels).
Biographical/Historical Note
1896 Born, Belgrade, Serbia
1905-1912 Attended Cadet School in Odessa, Russia. Graduated Military Academy (Artillery) in Petrograd, Russia
1914-1919 Served Serbian army in Serbia; twice wounded in action
1919-1921 Member of the Serbian military mission in Sofia, Bulgaria
1921-1923 Attended the Ecole supérieure de guerre in Paris, France
1924-1927 Served with a regiment in the Yugoslav Army, deployed to the general staff college in Belgrade, Yugoslavia
1927-1932 General staff officer on various assignments with the Yugoslav army, including a detail as Aide de Camp to His Majesty King Alexander of Yugoslavia
1932-1935 Military attaché in Rome, Italy
1935-1936 Chief of staff for an infantry division in Yugoslavia
1936-1940 Director of intelligence, general staff, Belgrade, Yugoslavia
1940-1941 Military Attaché in Moscow, U.S.S.R.
1941-1942 Director of intelligence, Yugoslav Force in Egypt
1942 Expelled from the Yugoslav Military after the Yugoslav army "Cairo Affair"
1942-1948 Commissioned by British military authority; served as Colonel with the British Forces in the Middle East in Egypt
1948-1949 Co-partner and chief translator at a translating office in London
1951-1952 Worked as an inspector with a South African insurance company in Nairobi, Kenya
1989 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers document events following World War II, reflecting primarily on the Yugoslav coup d'état of 27 March 1941, relations of the Yugoslav government-in-exile with the United States and Great Britain, the resistance movement, and dissension within the Yugoslav military (especially as expressed in the "Cairo Affair" of 1942), as well as developments in the Yugoslav army in the Middle East and postwar Yugoslav émigré politics. Includes diaries, in Russian, for the years 1917 to 1931 and 1941 to 1975.
The papers also include material on Draža Mihailović and the Yugoslav resistance movement during World War II as well as a considerable number of records that provide insight into Yugoslav foreign relations, particularly Yugoslav-Soviet relations.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into five series: Correspondence, Diaries, Speeches and writings, Subject file, and Yugoslav Military Attaché in the Soviet Union office file.
Access Points
Mihailović, Draža, 1893-1946.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Governments in exile.; World War, 1939-1945--Underground movements.; World War, 1939-1945--Yugoslavia.; Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--Foreign relations--Yugoslavia.; Yugoslavia.; Yugoslavia--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; Yugoslavia--History--Coup d'etat, 1941.; Yugoslavia--History--Axis occupation, 1941-1945.; Military attaches.; Yugoslavs--Great Britain.; Great Britain.
Container List
- Correspondence, 1940-1980 (Box 1)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Auchinleck, Claude, 1942 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Béthouart, General, 1974 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Fellers, Bonner, 1941-1953 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Fellers, Nancy, 1974 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Fortier, Louis, J. 1942-1953 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Jovanović, Slobodan, 1942 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Knezević, Zivan, 1942-1952 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Marković, Vladislav, 1952 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Mauran, Frank, Jr., 1942 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Molle, Marie-Eugène-Aimé, 1940-1952 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Nedić, Milan, 1940 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Stanko, 1969 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Vaso, reflecting on the Yugoslav army and World War II1976-1980. (Folder 1: 13)
  - Unsigned, 1942, 1949 (Folder 1: 14)
- Diaries, 1917-1975 (Folder 1)
  - February 1917-February 1931 (Folder 1: 15)
  - July 1941-May 1942 (Folder 1: 15)
  - May 1942-October 1942 (Folder 1: 15)
  - October 1942-27 July 1943 (Folder 1: 15)
  - June 1945-January 1948. Includes Zwei Reichsmark, Fünf Reichsmark bills (Folder 1: 16)
  - January 1948-December 1950 (Folder 1: 16)
  - January 1951-July 1953 (Folder 1: 16)
  - August 1953-September 1957 (Folder 1: 16)
  - October 1957-April 1962 (Folder 1: 16)
  - May 1962-February 1973 (Folder 2: 1)
  - February 1973-February 1975. Includes pressed wild flower (Folder 2: 2)
- Speeches and writings, 1940-1942 (Folder 2)
  - Untitled memoir from the U.S.S.R., 1940-1941 (Folder 23)
  - "Izveštaj o jačini i vrednosti Sovjetske vojne sile,", July 9, 1941 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Memorandum on Yugoslav-American cooperation in organizing and equipping an intelligence unit to operate in Yugoslavia, February 15, 1942 (Folder 2: 5)
  - "Moja služba u Sovjetskom Savezu,", undated (Folder 2: 6)
  - "Začetci Gansterizma u medjunarodnoj politici; ustaše u službi Musolinija,", undated (Folder 2: 7)
  - Letter to the editor "Oslobođenje,", undated (Folder 2: 8)
  - Notes, undated (Folder 2: 9)
- Subject file, 1940-1973. (Folder 2)
  Reports, memoranda, minutes, printed material and clippings, arranged alphabetically by title
  - General, 1940-1973 (Folder 2)
    - Burazović, Stjepan, 1971 (Folder 2: 10)
    - Chetniks, 1941 (Folder 2: 11)
  - Churchill, Winston, 1942 (Folder 2: 12)
    - "The Ciano Diaries 1939-1943," by Galeazzo Ciano, Italian Minister for Foreign Affairs, 1939-1943, transcript (Folder 2: 13)
    - Fotić, Konstatin, 1941 (Folder 2: 14)
    - Grol, Milan, undated (Folder 2: 15)
    - Knezević, Živan, 1942 (Folder 2: 16)
    - Mihailović, Draža, 1942, 1943 (Folder 2: 17)
    - Mirković, Borivoje, 1941, 1942 (Folder 2: 18)
    - Ninčić, Momčilo, 1942 (Folder 2: 19)
    - Partisans, undated (Folder 2: 20)
    - "Potpisivanje kapitulacije," Minutes of meeting of the Ministerial Council, Yugoslav Government, London, 30 January 1942 (Folder 2: 21)
    - Serbian Cultural Club, 1940 (Folder 2: 22)
    - Serbian Orthodox Church, 1941 (Folder 2: 23)
  - "Cairo Affair" materials, 1942-1943 (Folder 2)
    - General, 1941-1943 (Folder 2: 24-25)
    - British Government - Royal Yugoslavia agreement, 1942 (Folder 2: 26)
    - Causes and developments file, 1942 (Folder 3: 1)
    - Minutes of the British Military Authority Yugoslavia meeting, 1942 (Folder 3: 2)
    - Ž. Knežević, statement reports, 1942-1943 (Folder 3: 3)
    - Ž. Knežević, reports regarding D. Simović, B. Ilić, B. Mirković, Ž Popović, 1942 (Folder 3: 4)
    - Correspondence, 1941-1944 (Folder 3)
      - General, 1941-9144 (Folder 3: 5)
      - S. Jovanović to Eden, A., 1942 (Folder 3: 6)
      - S. Jovanović to Knežević, Ž., 1942 (Folder 3: 7)
      - S. Jovanović to Ninčić, K., 1942 (Folder 3: 8)
      - S. Jovanović to Rendel, G., 1942 (Folder 3: 9)
      - D. Simović to Churchill, W., 1942 (Folder 3: 10)
      - D. Simović to Mirković, B., 1941 (Folder 3: 11)
      - S. Živković to Cvetković, 1949, 1950 (Folder 3: 12)
  - Dušan Simović, 1941-1943, 1970 (Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1941-1943 (Folder 3: 13)
    - "Memoari Generala Simovića i dokumenti 1939-1942," by Vojimir Kljaković, Politika, August 21 - 24 November 1970 (Folder 3: 14-22)
  - Yugoslav army in the Middle East, 1941-1980 (Folder 3)
    - Anthony Eden, report on the developments in Yugoslav army crisis, 1942 (Folder 3: 23)
    - Appropriation of the state money among the Yugoslav army commanders, report, 1941 (Folder 3: 24)
    - Developments in the Yugoslav army, reports, 1942 (Folder 3: 25)
    - "Yugoslavia-Axis invasion, 1941," Politika, 1973 (Folder 3: 26)
  - Yugoslavia coup d'état on March 27, 1941, 1941-1973 (Folder 3)
    - Collected materials, 1941-1943, 1947, 1973 (Folder 3: 27, Folder 4: 1)
    - Paunović, Siniša, "Još jedna istina o 27 Martu 1941," Nin, February 20 - June 25, 1972 (Folder 4: 2)
  - Yugoslavia-Foreign relations, 1940-1942 (Folder 4)
    - Great Britain, 1941 (Folder 4: 3)
    - United States of America, 1941-1942 (Folder 4: 4)
    - General, Ilija Jukić (Folder 4)
      - "Kratak prikaz naše spoljne politike i opće međunarodne politike u toku 1940 i početkom 1941," by Ilija Jukić (Folder 4: 5)
      - "Razvitak naše spoljne politike i opće međunarod situacije od 14 Februara do 25 Marta 1941," by Ilija Jukić (Folder 4: 6)
      - "Naše pristupanje trojnom paktu, kartak pregled događaja," 1941, by Miloje Smiljanić (Folder 4: 7)
- Office File, Vojni Izaslanik Kraljevine Jugoslavije U.S.S.R., 1940-1941 (Box 4)
  Correspondence and reports by Zarko Popovic, Yugoslav Military Attaché in the Soviet Union, arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence, 1940-1941 (Box 4)
    - September 22, 1940 (Folder 4: 8)
    - October 1, 1940 (Folder 4: 9)
    - October 12, 1940 (Folder 4: 10)
    - October 20, 1940 (Folder 4: 11)
    - October 25, 1940 (Folder 4: 12)
    - October 30, 1940 (Folder 4: 13)
    - November 8, 1940 (Folder 4: 14)
    - November 22-26, 1940 (Folder 4: 15-20)
    - December 6-7, 1940 (Folder 4: 21-22)
    - (with enclosures dated November 16 and December 7), December 18, 1940 (Folder 4: 23)
    - January 15, 1941 (Folder 4: 24)
    - February 4-6, 1941 (Folder 4: 25-27)
    - March 3, 1941 (Folder 4: 28)
    - March 6, 1941 (Folder 4: 29)
    - March 7, 1941 (Folder 4: 30)
    - March 10, 1941 (Folder 4: 31)
    - March 14-15, 1941 (Folder 4: 32-33)
    - May 5, 1941 (Folder 4: 34)
    - May 31, 1941 (Folder 4: 35)
  - Gavrilović, Milan, correspondence from Moscow to Yugoslav Government, London, 1941 (Folder 4: 36)
  - Reports (Box 4)
    - Prvi Izveštaj (First Report), October 5, 1940 (Folder 4: 37)
    - Sovjetsko - Finski odnosi i vojno - politička delatnost S.S.S.R. (Soviet Finnish relations and military - political activity of the U.S.S.R.), November 10, 1940 (Folder 4: 38)
    - Drugi Mesečni Izveštaj (Second Monthly Report), November 10, 1940 (Folder 4: 39)
    - Materijal koji je potrebno nabaviti iz Rusije (Material to be purchased from Russia), November 11, 1940 (Folder 4: 40)
    - Treci Mesečni Izveštaj (Third Monthly Report), December 17, 1940 (Folder 4: 41)
    - Cetvrti Mesečni Izveštaj (Fourth Monthly Report), February 1, 1941 (Folder 4: 42)
    - Peti Mesečni Izveštaj (Fifth Monthly Report), March 24, 1941 (Folder 4: 43)
    - Pešadija (Infantry), March 24, 1941 (Folder 4: 44)
    - Sastav, jačinu i Razmeštaj vojske, March 25, 1941 (Folder 4: 45)